Guide to the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University records, 1920-1969
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University records 1920-1969
University Archives, Duke University
YMCA at Duke University.
0.75 Linear Feet 100 Items
The Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University was established at then Trinity College in 1887-1888. In its early years, it functioned primarily as a sort of Bible class. Although it never abandoned its emphasis on Christianity, in its later years the YMCA dedicated itself more to campus and social service projects than Bible study.
These records were produced by the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke Universityin the course of their activities as a student religious organization. Materials are present from 1920 to 1969; however, the bulk of the material is from the late 1930s to the early 1960s and consists mainly of annual reports. The majority of the remaining material consists of reports from other student religious organizations. Physical types of materials present include reports, pamphlets, correspondence, minutes, student publications, programs, flyers, and officer lists. There is one artifact, a gavel that is engraved with presidents' initials and years of service, 1945-1955.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke Universityrecords were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975, 1988, 1995.
Historical Note
The Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University was established at Trinity College in 1887-1888. In its early years, it functioned primarily as a sort of Bible class. Although it never abandoned its emphasis on Christianity, in its later years the YMCA dedicated itself more to campus and social service projects than Bible study. It was one of the largest and most influential of the student organizations. Activities for the years 1947-1967 include the Edgemont Community Center, Wright's Refuge, Freshman Orientation Week, publication of the student handbook, Religious Emphasis Week, Dads' Day, discussion groups, vespers services, Bible study, and student ushers for Duke Chapel. A Board of Directors composed of faculty and administration members oversaw the YMCA.
In 1969, the YMCA merged with the Young Women's Christian Association to form the YM-YWCA. Post-merger activities include draft counseling, Vietnam seminars and discussions, sponsorship of speakers and activists, promotion of Black Days, and so on. The organization ceased functioning in 1980-1981. See also issues of the Chanticleer, the Chronicle, and student handbooks as well as The Front Line: Materials for a Study of Leadership in College and After by Ben M. Patrick (Duke University, 1938) for more historical details. See YM-YWCA Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action and YWCA materials for more detail on collaborative activities in the 1960s-1970s.
Collection Overview
These records were produced by the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University in the course of their activities as a student religious organization. Materials are present from 1920 to 1969; however, the bulk of the material is from the late 1930s to the early 1960s and consists mainly of annual reports. The majority of the remaining material consists of reports from other student religious organizations. Physical types of materials present include reports, pamphlets, correspondence, minutes, student publications, programs, flyers, and officer lists. There is one artifact, a gavel that is engraved with presidents' initials and years of service, 1945-1955.
The majority of the records consist of reports of campus student religious organizations, and annual reports prepared by YMCA officers, which date from 1936-1967, although they are not inclusive. The annual reports summarize YMCA activities and projects from the past school year, and offer suggestions for the next year. See also catalogued and bound reports at call number 378.756 D887FA. There are two reports generated by the YMCA in the course of their campus activities: a proposal regarding the Freshman Advisory Council and a report on the success of the 1948 fund drive for the World Student Service Fund (WSSF). For more information on the incorporation of the Freshman Advisory Council (FAC) into the YMCA, see the annual report from 1957-1958. The remaining reports were created by other student religious organizations such as the Hillel Society (for Jewish students), the Baptist Student Union, and the YWCA. Correspondence is limited to one item. "Dads' Day" items consist of programs and schedules for the annual fathers' weekend. See also programs at call number 378.756 D887FD.
Publications are limited to examples of the student handbook and the "Dink," a daily publication for freshmen produced during Freshman Orientation Week. For other student handbooks see call number 378.756 D877S. For discussions of activities related to desegregation at Duke, see annual reports 1959-1960 and 1967-1968. Draft counseling materials are limited to announcements of seminars and conferences. For discussions of Vietnam and the selective service system, see annual reports of 1966-1967 and 1967-1968. For more information on Vietnam, the draft, and the counseling center, see YWCA and YM-YWCA Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action materials. Although there are no membership lists, there are quite inclusive lists of officers from 1888-1936 and 1956-1957.
Collection Arrangement
Loose materials and bound reports are arranged alphabetically by subject. Items within the folders are arranged chronologically. The two largest series of records, annual reports and reports of other organizations, are arranged chronologically within the series.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College student orientation -- North Carolina -- Durham -- 1947-1967.
College students -- Alcohol use -- 1939.
College students -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Religious life
Duke University. Freshman Advisory Council
Duke University -- Students -- Public services -- 1920-1969.
Edgemont Community Center (Durham, NC)
Wright's Refuge (Durham, NC)
YMCA of the USA
Related Material
William Wade "Cap" Card papers, 1918-1919.
University Archives, Duke University.
Young Men's--Young Women's Christian Association.
University Archives, Duke University.
Young Women's Christian Association records, 1908-1971.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 1 Box
  - Annual Report (incomplete) 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report 1947-1948
  - Annual Report (condensed) 1947-1948
  - Annual Report 1949-1950
  - Annual Report 1950-1951
  - Annual Report 1951-1952
  - Annual Report 1952-1953
  - Annual Report 1953-1954
  - Annual Report 1954-1955
  - Annual Report 1955-1956
  - Annual Report 1957-1958
  - Annual Report 1959-1960
  - Annual Report 1966-1967
  - Committee on Research and Analysis 1969
  - Correspondence 1935
  - "Dads' Day" 1954; 1958-1960; 1962-1964
  - Draft Counseling 1966; 1969
  - Minutes, YMCA Board of Directors October 2, 1956
  - Officer Lists 1888-1936; 1956-1957
  - Programs or Announcements of YMCA Sponsored Events, 1921; 1929; 1931; 1935; 1938; 1944; 1967; n.d.
  - Publications, "Dink" 1957
  - Publications, Duke University Handbook 1920-1921; 1964-1965; 1968-1969
  - "Report from the YMCA on the Possibilities of Transferring the Freshman Advisory Council to a Place in the Organization of the YMCA" March 1, 1957
  - "Report of the World Student Service Fund Organization" 1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, School of Religion, Student Body Activity Report 1939-1940
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Semi-Annual Report, May 1944
  - Westminster Fellowship
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Annual Report, Hillel Society 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Annual Report, Westminster Fellowship 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Annual Reports of Campus Religious Organizations (incomplete) 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, East Campus World Student Service Fund Drive 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, President's Report, Baptist Student Union 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Vespers Schedule of Meetings, School of Nursing 1947-1948
  - Reports of Other Organizations, Report of Young Women's Christian Association 1948-1949
  - Gavel1945-1955